Ares is the best person I've ever known.
Ares adalah orang terbaik yang pernah aku kenal.
He's so loyal to the gang.
Dia selalu membela anggota Calderioz.
He never lets anyone down.
Dia tak pernah membiarkan anggota Calderioz kesulitan.
He's the opposite of what he's showing to us...
Dia tak seperti penampilannya...
being solemn and cold.
yang terlihat menyebalkan dan pendiam.
But, deep down he has a gentle heart.
Namun, dia sangat perhatian.
A sunflower, a symbol of loyalty.
Bunga matahari melambangkan kesetiaan.
Look. The yellow part represents warmth and happiness.
Lihat, warna kuning identik dengan kehangatan dan kebahagiaan.
But, I will always be...
Namun, aku...
a prisoner in your heart till the day that I die.
akan selalu terpenjara di hatimu sampai mati.
-Make way! -Aiden!
- Menyingkirlah! - Aiden!
Aiden!
Aiden!
Den!
Den!
-Aiden! -Moreo, stop!
- Aiden! - Sudahlah, Moreo!
Aiden!
Aiden!
Sorry, please wait outside.
Maaf, silakan tunggu di luar.
-Aiden! -Stop it, Mor!
- Aiden! - Sudah, Mor!
Serra, tell me what happened.
Serra, beri tahu aku apa yang terjadi.
Did you see the license plate?
Kau melihat pelat nomor motornya?
Did you see the guy?
Kau melihat seperti apa pelakunya?
Please, you have to tell me!
Ser, beri tahu aku!
Let her calm herself down.
Biarkan Serra menenangkan diri lebih dulu.
Serra...
Serra...
You just relax.
Tenanglah.
After Aiden survives the critical phase,...
Saat Aiden sudah melewati masa kritis,...
then we'll get our revenge.
kita akan mengurus semua ini.
My son!
Putraku!
What happened to my son?
Bagaimana bisa begitu?
Tell me what happened to my son?
Apa yang terjadi kepada putraku?
My son...
Putraku...
How could this happen?
Bagaimana ini bisa terjadi?
What if he doesn't make it?
Bagaimana jika dia tak selamat?
Calm down. Let's just pray for the best.
Bersabarlah. Kita doakan yang terbaik untuk Aiden.
I haven't had enough time to make him happy.
Aku belum cukup membahagiakan Aiden.
I'm sorry, Aiden.
Maaf, Aiden.
-How is my son? -How is it?
- Bagaimana putraku, Dok? - Bagaimana, Dok?
I'm sorry, sir, ma'am.
Maaf, Pak, Bu.
We have tried our best.
Kami sudah berusaha yang terbaik.
But, unfortunately, we couldn't save your son.
Namun, putra kalian tak bisa kami selamatkan.
What do you mean you couldn't save my son?
Apa maksudnya tak bisa diselamatkan?
I can't lose my son!
Bagaimana, Dok? Aku tak bisa kehilangan putraku!
Doctor, please!
Tolong, Dokter!
I'm sorry, son. I wish I could suffer in your place.
Maaf, Sayang. Ibu saja yang sakit.
God, please take me instead.
Biar Ibu saja yang menggantikanmu.
Don't take my son away.
Jangan mengambil putraku.
I'm sorry, Aiden...
Maaf, Aiden...
Aiden, babe. Please, wake up.
Aiden, Sayang. Ayo bangun.
Hold this and put this on my hair.
Pegang ini dan pasangkan di rambutku sekarang.
You hear me, right? Aiden, please. Do you hear me?
Kau mendengarku, 'kan? Aiden, ayo bangun.
You promised me that you're going to put this on my hair.
Aiden, kau berjanji mau memasangkan ini di rambutku.
You have to wake up! You promised me! Don't you remember?
Aiden, bangun! Kau sudah berjanji! Kau ingat?
Aiden! No, no, no!
Aiden! Tidak!
No! Let me go! He can't leave me now!
Tidak! Lepaskan! Aiden tak boleh meninggalkanku!
Aiden, please. Who will take care of me now?
Aiden, aku mohon. Siapa yang akan menjagaku sekarang?
Aiden, please wake up.
Aiden, bangunlah.
Serra?
Serra?
Serra, wake up!
Serra, bangun!
Goddamn it!
Bajingan!
Ares, stop it!
Ares, berhenti!
Aiden can't die like this.
Aiden tak bisa meninggal seperti ini.
Who did this to him?
Siapa yang berani melakukan ini?
Which gang?
Geng motor siapa?
I'm going to hunt them and finish them!
Aku akan mencari dan menghabisi mereka!
I'm going to kill them all!
Aku akan menghabisi mereka sekarang!
-Stop! -Get your hands off me!
- Berhenti! - Lepaskan aku!
You told us, remember?
Kau sendiri yang mengatakannya!
We need proof before doing anything.
Kita harus mencari bukti lebih dulu sebelum bertindak.
Ares, stop!
Ares, berhenti!
I won't let you leave before you can control your anger.
Selama emosimu tak terkendali, aku takkan mengizinkanmu pergi.
Anger won't solve anything.
Emosi takkan menyelesaikan masalah.
Let me go!
Lepaskan aku!
Don't let your emotions control you!
Jangan memakai emosi!
Use your brain.
Pakai otakmu!
Whoa, watch out!
Hei, Zea. Awas!
-That's crazy. -Who did that?
- Dasar gila. - Siapa itu?
-Are you okay? -Yeah.
- Kau aman, 'kan? - Ya.
Here, let me help you.
Ini, aku akan membantumu.
Sorry.
Maaf.
Zea?
Zea?
Lio?
Lio?
I was visiting my friend and then I saw you.
Aku tadi sedang menjenguk temanku, lalu melihatmu di sini.
What are you doing here?
Apa yang kau lakukan di sini?
My friend passed away.
Temanku meninggal, Kak.
Zea...
Zea...
You have to be strong.
Kau harus bersabar.
Why?
Kenapa?
Why does someone with a gentle heart have to go so soon?
Kenapa harus orang sebaik dia yang pergi?
And why did he have to go like that?
Kenapa dengan cara seperti itu?
Do you think that...
Menurutmu...
Calderioz' accusation to Retro angered them?
apa mungkin tuduhan Calderioz kepada Retro membuat Retro marah?
Where there's smoke, there's fire.
Saat ada asap, pasti ada api.
Just like how Calderioz has their enemies.
Seperti Calderioz memiliki musuh, Zea.
I don't know.
Aku tak tahu.
But, I know for sure that Aiden didn't deserve to die like this.
Namun, yang pasti Kak Aiden tak pantas pergi dengan cara seperti ini.
No!
Tidak!
Mor.
Mor.
Calm yourself down.
Jangan berteriak, Mor.
This is a hospital.
Ini rumah sakit.
You guys are pulling a prank, right?
Kalian pasti bergurau kepadaku, 'kan?
Okay, guys. Enough of this. This is just a prank, right?
Sudahlah, jangan bergurau. Benar, 'kan?
Mor. I know you're sad.
Mor. Aku tahu kau merasa sedih.
Because we are, too.
Kita sama.
Aiden was a part of Calderioz.
Aiden bagian dari Calderioz.
We all lost him. Not only you.
Kita semua merasa kehilangan dia, Mor. Tak hanya dirimu.
All of this is happening...
Semua ini sudah terjadi...
I think it's fate.
Ini sudah takdir.
Den.
Den.
Please don't leave us.
Jangan meninggalkan kami, Den.
Mor. Calm down.
Mor. Tenanglah.
He's happy where he is now.
Aiden sudah bahagia di sana.
You should let him go.
Kau harus mengikhlaskannya.
For you who has left this world,...
Untukmu yang meninggalkan Bumi,...
you should not be afraid of feeling lonely.
tak perlu khawatir akan sepi.
You should not worry about being alone.
Tak perlu cemas perihal sendiri.
We will see each other again one day.
Kita akan berjumpa di lain hari.
To be together with you again.
Bercengkerama denganmu lagi.
Letting you go, even with doubts...
Mengikhlaskan kepergian dirimu, meski ragu,...
we are ready to carry this yearn,...
kami siap menanggung rindu.
and to walk without you.
Serta siap berjalan tanpamu.
From Calderioz to Aiden.
Dari Calderioz untuk Aiden.
You know where that curiosity leads to.
Kau tahu dari penasaran akan ke arah mana?
To your heart. Be careful.
Ke perasaanmu. Hati-hati.
And I know that...
Aku yakin malam ini...
you will remember this night for the rest of your lives.
tak pernah terlupakan oleh kalian semua.
Calderioz is where I find joy,...
Calderioz adalah tempatku tertawa,...
sadness, and rise.
menangis, dan terbangun.
You will always be in our hearts, Den.
Kau akan selalu berada di hati kami sampai kapan pun, Den.
You were everything to Calderioz.
Kau adalah segalanya bagi Calderioz.
I can feel his pain.
Aku bisa merasakan kesakitan Aiden.
Are you okay, Ares?
Kau tak apa, Ares?
I'm okay.
Tak apa.
Welcome to Calderioz headquarters!
Selamat datang di markas Calderioz!
I like this one. What do you think?
Aku suka ini. Bagaimana menurutmu?
You should calm down a bit.
Kau harus menjadi sedikit lebih tenang.
Be patient. I will be right back, okay, guys?
Bersabarlah. Aku akan segera kembali.
That was...
Tadi namanya...
You think you're that handsome? Your face looks like a duck.
Kau pikir kau tampan? Wajahmu terlihat seperti bebek.
-Stop the vlog. Let me handle it. -What are you doing? I'm not done yet!
- Berhenti membuat vlog. Aku saja. -Apa yang kau lakukan? Belum selesai!
Aiden's death made me afraid.
Kematian Kak Aiden membuatku merasa takut.
I'm afraid that Ardhan's going that way too.
Aku merasa takut bahwa Ardhan akan mengalami kejadian yang sama.
I know,...
Aku tahu,...
Ardhan can't be separated from Calderioz.
Ardhan tak bisa dipisahkan dari Calderioz.
But, I'm afraid...
Namun, aku takut...
that the death of Aiden...
hal yang dialami Kak Aiden...
will start a war between Calderioz with other gangs.
akan memulai peperangan antara Calderioz dengan geng motor lain.
Calderioz is not that kind of bike gang.
Calderioz bukan geng motor seperti itu.
They wouldn't start making trouble.
Mereka pasti takkan memulai masalah.
Okay?
Ya?
Right now,...
Saat ini,...
all you can do is to calm Ardhan.
kau hanya bisa menenangkan Kak Ardhan.
I'm sure Calderioz is in the middle of confusion now.
Aku yakin perasaan Calderioz sedang kacau saat ini.
Angry, sad,...
Merasa marah, sedih,...
lost, and also trying to find justice for Aiden.
kehilangan, juga mencari keadilan untuk Aiden.
-So, it's okay if I'm afraid, right? -That's okay.
- Jadi, wajar jika aku merasa takut? - Itu wajar.
Please join us.
Datanglah.
-Please join us. -Thanks, Zea.
- Datanglah. - Terima kasih, Zea.
Please join us.
Datanglah.
Serra isn't coming to school again.
Serra tak masuk sekolah lagi.
She must be devastated.
Dia pasti sangat sedih.
She needs us.
Dia membutuhkan kita.
How about visiting her tomorrow?
Bagaimana jika besok kita ke rumah Serra?
Sure.
Aku setuju.
(Ceremonial Prayer Invitation)
(Undangan Baca Doa Bersama)
Aiden.
Aiden.
I still can't believe you're not with us anymore.
Aku masih tak percaya bahwa kau sudah tak ada.
This is my only picture with you.
Ini satu-satunya fotoku denganmu.
This photo will be a memento for me.
Foto ini menjadi kenanganmu dengan Mang Oji.
So, I will never forget about you.
Jadi, aku akan mengingatmu.
Den, I will remember you forever.
Den, aku akan mengingatmu selamanya.
I miss you, Aiden.
Aku merindukanmu, Aiden.
Nobody knows whose turn is next.
Umur seseorang memang tak ada yang tahu.
I know that you'll be here.
Aku tahu Kak Megan pasti ke sini.
Because this place is full of memory of Aiden.
Karena tempat ini dipenuhi kenangan akan Kak Aiden.
Everyone have their own way to cope with their sadness.
Semua orang memiliki caranya sendiri untuk mengusir kesedihannya.
If you need someone to talk to, you've got me.
Jika kau membutuhkan teman berbicara, ada aku.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
Peace be upon you too.
Wa'alaikumussalam.
We're all here to mourn...
Kita semua di sini turut berduka cita...
one of our students who has just passed away.
atas meninggalnya salah satu murid.
Let this be a lesson to all of us for the better in the future.
Ini semua pelajaran agar kita menjadi yang terbaik ke depannya.
We pray that...
Semoga...
he may rest in peace with Allah as well as he deserved.
Almarhum diterima di sisi Allah SWT dan ditempatkan selayaknya.
Amen.
Amin.
On behalf of Aiden,...
Aku mewakili Aiden.
if he ever hurt your feelings, or played a prank on you,...
Jika Aiden memiliki salah terhadap kalian, pernah menjahili,...
please forgive him.
tolong maafkan dia.
We have to catch Aiden's killer and make him pay for what he did.
Kita harus menangkap dan mengadili pembunuh Aiden.
Aye!
Tentu!
Always remember the three rules of Calderioz.
Jangan pernah melupakan tiga aturan Calderioz.
Defend each member.
Membela tiap anggota.
Destroy the betrayer.
Menghancurkan pengkhianat.
Don't die as a loser.
Jangan mati sebagai pecundang.
Laskar.
Laskar.
I need you to set up a plan.
Siapkan sebuah rencana.
We need to check all of the other bike gang headquarters.
Kita akan memeriksa satu per satu markas geng motor lainnya.
We have to find out who did this to him.
Kita akan mencari dalang di balik peristiwa ini.
To get justice for Aiden.
Untuk mendapatkan keadilan bagi Aiden.
You, you, and you, come with me.
Kau, kau, dan kau, ikut denganku.
How are you doing, Serra?
Bagaimana kabarmu, Serra?
We're worried about you.
Kami semua mengkhawatirkanmu.
Yeah, I kept thinking of you.
Ya, aku terus memikirkanmu.
I'm sure Aiden wouldn't want to see us sad like this.
Aiden pasti tak mau melihat kita bersedih.
Right?
Ya, 'kan?
Let me get you a drink.
Aku akan menyiapkan minuman untuk kalian.
I hope she's really okay.
Semoga dia sungguh tak apa.
Yeah. I feel really bad for her.
Ya. Aku merasa sungguh tak tega melihatnya.